Welcome back to Apush in under 3
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. So, it's 1845 and James K. Polk
is elected president. If there is one
thing you should know about this guy, it
is that he cared only about one thing,
westward expansion. He started by
negotiating with Britain to secure
Oregon up to the 49th parallel. This
would avoid war while expanding the US
Northwest. But, here's the thing, as
America expanded, tensions with Mexico
escalated over the Texas border. The US
claimed the Rio Grande, while Mexico
insisted it was the new Nueces River.
Polk sent troops into the disputed
Texas-Mexico border, and after a
skirmish, he claimed, quote, "American
blood was shed on American soil." He
used this as a justification to declare
war in what was known as the
Mexican-American War. After the US
captured some major cities and blockaded
Mexico, which cripples its economy, they
end up winning the war. This war would
end with the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo
in 1848. And while this treaty did a lot
of things, what you should know is that
it gave the US a lot of land, like a lot
of land. This land was known as the
Mexican Cession. And the issue of
whether each state would be slave or
free would need to be solved further at
something known as the Compromise of
1850. It should also be noted that US
interaction and conflict with American
Indians and Mexican-Americans would
increase because of the westward
expansion. These often resulted in many
unfair treaties, or in the case of Sand
Creek, it would lead to a bloody
massacre where hundreds were said to
have been slaughtered in 1864. On the
screen now are some AP-style questions
for this topic. Pause now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.